Guide to the Martha Pennino papers, 1960-2005
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Martha Pennino papers
1960-2005
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Martha Pennino, 1918-2004
C0146
12.5 linear feet (25 boxes)
The Martha Pennino papers document Pennino's career on Fairfax County Board of Supervisors. Within the collection there are photographs, information from different projects that Martha Pennino worked on during her career and memorabilia that Martha Pennino collected during and after her career. The collection is dated from the early 1960s to 2005.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Martha Pennino in September 1992.
Biographical Information
Born in Roanoke, Virginia, Martha Pennino (1918-2004) was called the Mother of Fairfax for her long service to the county. She was one of the longest-serving members of the Fairfax County Board of Supervisors, spending 24 years on the board. She was first elected in November 1967, representing what was then the Centreville District. She served as vice chairman for a total of 17 years.
In 1985, Pennino won the Tom Bradley Regional Leadership Award. In giving her this honor, the National Association of Regional Councils cited her efforts in developing the first energy policy for a metropolitan area, the first area car pool program, and a fair share housing program. In 1986, Washingtonian magazine named her Washingtonian of the Year. Prior to joining the board, Pennino was elected to three terms on the Vienna Town Council, serving as vice mayor during one of those terms. Additionally, Pennino took a leadership role in developing the planned community of Reston, as well as embracing low-cost housing adjacent to her office.
Scope and Content
The Martha Pennino Collection documents Pennino's career on Fairfax County Board of Supervisors. Within the collection there are photographs, information from different projects that Martha Pennino worked on during her career and memorabilia that Martha Pennino collected during and after her career. The collection is dated from the early 1960s to 2005.
Series one is organized in alphabetical order. This collection is mostly paperwork relating to different projects, such as subsidizing, transportation, and the Reston Community Association. The series is dated from 1971-1990.
Series two is comprised of newsclippings. They are organized chronologically by month and year. The newsclipping cover Martha Pennino career such as Pennino's campaigns, re-elections and community meetings. The series is dated from 1960-1989.
Series three includes photographs that document Martha Pennino's career. The photographs show Martha Pennino campaigning, attending receptions and meeting with well know politicians including President Jimmy Carter and Senator Ted Kennedy. The series is dated from 1960-1985.
Series four is memorabilia that Martha Pennino collected. Items in this series include awards from different organizations such as Fox Mill Communities Preservation Association and Vienna Little League. Also in the collection is a telegram from President Jimmy Carter and a letter from John Glenn. The series is dated from 1960-2005.
Series five is oversize. It includes three boxes of memorabilia from Martha Pennino. Included are posters and awards given to Martha Pennino. The series is dated from 1960-1992.
Arrangement
Organized into 5 series.
Series 1: Subject Files, 1971-1990 (Boxes 1-12)
Series 2: Newsclippings, 1960-1989 (Boxes 12-18)
Series 3: Photographs, 1960-1985 (Box 19)
Series 4: Memorabilia, 1960-2005 (Boxes 20-22)
Series 5: Oversize, 1960-1992 (Boxes 23-25)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
The Special Collections and Archives also holds the Planned Community Archives and other personal papers and organizational records that document Reston, Virginia, and other planned communities.
Index Terms
Persons:
Pennino, Martha, 1918-2004.
Corporate Names:
Fairfax County (Va.). Board of Supervisors.
Geographical Names:
Fairfax County (Va.)--Politics and government.; Reston (Va.)
Subjects:
Housing--Virginia--Fairfax County.; Local government--Virginia--Fairfax County.
Contents List
- Series 1: Subject Files, 1970-1991
  This is the largest series in the collection and is organized in alphabetic order. In the series there is information on subsidizing housing, transportation, rezoning and other items relating to the work that Martha Pennino did while a member of the Board of Supervisors in Fairfax County.
  - Bowman Distillery, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    244.3
  - Bowman Distillery, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    244.2
  - Bowman Distillery, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    244.1
  - Buses: Reston Community Buses, 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    252.4
  - Buses: Reston Community Buses, 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    252.5
  - Buses: Reston Community Buses, 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    252.6
  - Buses: Reston Community Buses, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    252.7
  - Buses: Reston Community Buses, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    252.8
  - Buses: Reston Internal Bus System, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    253.3
  - Buses: Reston Internal Bus System, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    253.2
  - Buses: Reston Internal Bus System, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    253.1
  - Economic Impact of Reston on County, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    250.3
  - Embry Rucker Shelter, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    248.1
    - Dedication Ceremony - Embry Rucker Shelter for the Homeless, May 3, 1989; 1.
    - Dedication Lake Anne Elementary School, April 30, 1967; 2.
  - Fox Mill/Stonegate, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    254.4
  - Fox Mill/Stonegate, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    254.3
  - Fox Mill/Stonegate, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    254.2
  - Island Walk Subsidized Housing, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    245.1
  - Island Walk Subsidized Housing, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    244.4
  - Island Walk Subsidized Housing, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    244.7
  - Island Walk Subsidized Housing, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    244.8
  - Island Walk Subsidized Housing, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    244.6
  - Island Walk Subsidized Housing, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    244.5
  - Parcel 5-A, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    250.1
  - Parcel 5-A, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    250.2
  - Parcel 12-B Waterford Apartments, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    246.5
  - Parcel 12-A, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    249.7
  - Parcel 12-B Waterford Apartments, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    246.4
  - Plat Showing Street Dedication of Fairfax Parkway, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    253.4
  - Reston Community Association, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    249.4
  - Reston Community Association, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    249.6
  - Reston Community Association, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    249.5
  - Reston Community Center, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    248.5
  - Reston Community Center, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    248.7
  - Reston Community Center, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    248.6
  - Reston Community Center, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    248.2
  - Reston Community Center, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    245.6
  - Reston Community Center, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    245.5
  - Reston Governance, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    250.8
  - Reston Governance, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    250.9
  - Reston Governance, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    251.9
  - Reston Governance, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    250.7
  - Reston Master Plan, 1970s (Box 6, Folder 3)
    250.4
  - Reston Master Plan, 1970s (Box 6, Folder 4)
    250.5
  - Reston Master Plan and Transportation Plan, 1970s (Box 6, Folder 5)
    250.6
  - Reston Planned Community Zone, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    255.4
  - Rezoning, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    255.1
  - Rezoning, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    255.2
  - Rezonings, 1984-1985 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    255.3
  - Russian Statue, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    247.1
  - Russian Statue, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    247.2
  - Russian Statue, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    247.3
  - Russian Statue, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    247.5
  - Russian Statue, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    247.4
  - Sister City: Nyeri, Kenya, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    247.8
  - Sister City: Nyeri, Kenya, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    247.7
    - Reston/Nyeri Sister City Committee Report to Reston Community Association, April 22, 1985; 1.
  - Sister City: Nyeri, Kenya, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    247.6
    - Reston - Nyeria Sister City Program, June 19, 1986; 1.
  - Stonegate, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    251.6
  - Stonegate, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    251.7
  - Stonegate, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    251.8
  - Stonegate, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    252.1
  - Stonegate, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    252.2
  - Stonegate, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    252.3
  - Stonegate Task Force, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    251.1
  - Street Lights, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    249.3
  - Street Lights, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    249.2
  - Street Lights, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    249.1
  - Street Lights, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    248.8
  - Subsidized Housing: Fox Mill/Stonegate, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    248.4
  - Subsidized Housing: Fox Mill/Stonegate, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Subsidized Housing: Fox Mill/Stonegate, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    248.3
  - Subsidized Housing: Miscellaneous, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    251.5
  - Subsidized Housing: Miscellaneous, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    251.3
  - Subsidized Housing: Miscellaneous, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    251.4
  - Symposium, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    251.2
  - Town Center, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    253.7
  - Town Center, 1990s (Box 10, Folder 4)
    253.5
  - Town Center, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    253.6
  - Town Government: Incorporation, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    245.2
  - Town Government: Incorporation, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    245.3
  - Town Government: Incorporation, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    245.4
  - Transportation, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    243.3
  - Transportation, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    243.1
  - Transportation, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    243.2
  - Twentieth Anniversary, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    254.1
    - Reston 20th Anniversary Symposium Paper, May 1985; 6.
  - Virginia Electric and Power Company: Power Outages, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    243.7
  - Virginia Electric and Power Company: Power Outages, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    243.6
  - Virginia Electric and Power Company: Power Outages, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    243.5
  - Virginia Electric and Power Company: Power Outages, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    243.4
  - Waterbridge, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    246.6
  - Wiehle Avenue Bridge, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    254.5
  - Wiehle Avenue Bridge, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    254.6
- Series 2: Newsclippings, 1960-1989
  This series is comprised of newsclippings over the course of Martha Pennino career. The newsclippings are in chronological order, organized by year. The newsclippings cover a variety of topics including campaigning and re-election.
  - Newsclippings, 1960s (Box 12, Folder 5)
    256.9
  - Newsclippings, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    256.7
  - Newsclippings, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    256.6
  - Newsclippings, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    256.1
  - Newsclippings, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    256.2
  - Newsclippings, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    256.3
  - Newsclippings, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    256.4
  - Newsclippings, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    256.5
  - Newsclippings, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    256.8
  - Newsclippings, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    257.1
  - Newsclippings, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    257.2
  - Newsclippings, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    257.3
  - Newsclippings, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    257.4
  - Newsclippings, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    257.5
  - Newsclippings, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    257.6
  - Newsclippings, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    257.7
  - Newsclippings, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    257.8
  - Newsclippings, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    258.1
  - Newsclippings, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    258.2
  - Newsclippings, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    258.3
  - Newsclippings, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    258.4
  - Newsclippings, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    258.5
  - Newsclippings, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    258.6
  - Newsclippings, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    258.7
  - Newsclippings, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    258.8
  - Newsclippings, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    259.1
  - Newsclippings, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    259.2
  - Newsclippings, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    259.3
  - Newsclippings, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    259.4
  - Newsclippings, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    259.5
  - Newsclippings, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    259.6
  - Newsclippings, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    259.7
  - Newsclippings, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    259.8
  - Newsclippings, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    260.1
  - Newsclippings, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    260.2
  - Newsclippings, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    260.3
  - Newsclippings, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    260.4
  - Newsclippings, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    260.5
  - Newsclippings, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    261.1
  - Newsclippings, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    261.2
  - Newsclippings, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    261.3
  - Newsclippings, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    261.4
  - Newsclippings, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    261.5
  - Newsclippings, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    261.6
  - Newsclippings, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    262.1
  - Newsclippings, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    262.2
  - Newsclippings, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    262.3
  - Newsclippings, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    262.4
  - Newsclippings, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    262.5
  - Newsclippings, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    262.6
  - Newsclippings, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    262.7
  - Newsclippings, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    263.1
  - Newsclippings, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    263.2
  - Newsclippings, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    263.3
  - Newsclippings, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    263.4
  - Newsclippings, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    263.5
  - Newsclippings, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    263.6
  - Newsclippings, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    264.1
  - Newsclippings, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    264.2
  - Newsclippings, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    264.3
  - Newsclippings, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    264.4
  - Newsclippings, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    264.5
  - Newsclippings, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    264.6
  - Newsclippings, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    264.7
  - Newsclippings, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Newsclippings, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Newsclippings, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Newsclippings, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Newsclippings, 1988-1989 (Box 18, Folder 8)
- Series 3: Photographs, 1960-1985
  This series is comprised of photographs that cover Martha Pennino entire career in Fairfax. Most of the photographs are of meetings, dedication ceremonies and receiptions.
  - Campaigning, Board of Supervisors, John Glenn, 1960s-1970s (Box 19, Folder 1)
    5.9
  - Wedding, Campaigning, Dedication Ceremonies, 1960s-1980s (Box 19, Folder 2)
    5.6
  - Autograph from Thomson Hirst, Dedication Ceremonies, 1970s-1980s (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Meetings, Receptions, Dedication Ceremonies, 1970s (Box 19, Folder 4)
    5.11
  - Campaigning, Dedication Ceremonies, 1970s (Box 19, Folder 5)
    5.10
  - Luncheon, Carnival, Board of Supervisors Meetings, 1974 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    5.1
  - Meeting, Ceremonies, includes President Jimmy Carter and Senator Ted Kennedy, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    5.2
  - Groundbreaking, Ceremonies, Campaigning for Re-election, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    5.3
  - Martha Pennino and Gatherings, 1980s (Box 19, Folder 9)
    5.5
  - Martha Pennino at Various Location, 1980s (Box 19, Folder 10)
    5.8
  - Receptions, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    5.4
  - Washingtonian of the Year, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    5.12
- Series 4: Memorabilia, 1960-2005
  This series is comprised of memorabilia that Martha Pennino received during and after her career. Included in the collection are magazine articles and awards from different organizations in recognization for her work over the years.
  - Study for Martha Pennino (Block Print), 1974 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    3.2
  - Vienna Little League, 1975-1976 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    3.1
  - Golden Spike Ceremony, 1978 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    3.3
  - Northern Virginia Youth Services Coalition, 1987 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    3
  - Fox Mill Communities Preservation Association, 1991 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    3.4
  - Martha Pennino Portrait, 1980s (Box 20, Folder 6)
    3.5
  - A Reception to HOnor Martha V. Pennino, 1991 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    3.6
  - Certificate of Appreciation, 1991 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Women of the Year Martha V. Pennino, 1986 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    2.1
  - The Vienna Jaycees, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    2.2
  - James Madison High School, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    2.3
  - Rotary Foundation of Rotary International Paul Harris Fellow with medal, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    2.4
  - Certificates of Appreciation, 1960-1990s (Box 22, Folder 1)
    6.4
  - Walter Washington and Jack Nevius's Signatures, 1970s-1980s (Box 22, Folder 2)
    6.14
  - Pins, 1970s-1980s (Box 22, Folder 3)
    6.18
  - Cartoons, 1970s (Box 22, Folder 4)
    6.3
  - Newsclippings, 1974 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    6.13
  - Campaign Brochure, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    6.10
  - Telegram from President Jimmy Carter, 1978 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    6.8
  - Fisher Reception, 1979 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    6.12
  - Reston 20th Anniversary Commendation, 1982 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    6.5
  - The Washingtonian Luncheon Invitation, 1982 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    6.11
  - Washingtonian of the Year, 1985 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    6.1
  - Transcript of a Portion of the Board of Supervisors Meeting, 1985 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    6.6
  - Remarks by Fairfax County Executive J. Hamilton Lambert to Northern Virginia Board of Realtors Strategic Planning Committee, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    6.17
  - AMC Cancer Research Center Roast, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 14)
    6.2
  - Letter from Annie and John Glenn, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 15)
    6.9
  - Letter from George P. Shultz, 1988 (Box 22, Folder 16)
    6.16
  - Magazines, 1986-1989 (Box 22, Folder 17)
    6.7
  - Martha Pennino Reston Post Office Building Dedication Ceremony, 2005 (Box 22, Folder 18)
    6.15
- Series 5: Oversize, 1972-1992
  This series includes 3 boxes. The oversized boxes are stored separate from the rest of the collection. The documents included are posters and awards that were given to Martha Pennino.
  - Pennino Tribute, 1992 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    399
  - Posters, 1980s (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Bicentennial, 1976 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    1
  - Electoral Board of Fairfax County Certificate, 1975 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Reston Community Association Recognization, 1970s (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Electoral Board of Fairfax County Certificate, 1987 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Electoral Board of Fairfax County Certificate, 1983 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Board of Visitors of George Mason Univeristy, 1989 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Cartoon, 1977 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Washingtonian Plat, 1985 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Toastmasters International Communication Achievement Award, 1985 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Resolution from the Medical Staff, Board of Trustees and Administration of Reston Hospital Center in honor of Martha V. Pennino, 1989 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Framed Virginia Review, 1989 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Photograph, Fairfax County Park Services, 1972 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    2
  - Photograph, Martha Pennino and President Jimmy Carter, 1970s (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments Award, 1978 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments Award, 1972 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments Award, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Tom Bradley Regional Leadership Award, 1985 (Box 25, Folder 6)